Guide to the Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence Editorial Project Records
The Lewis Walpole Library
Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence Editorial Project Records
1900-1983
1936-1983
LWL MSS 23
The Lewis Walpole Library
49.6
92 boxes + 3 broadsides + 1 roll
The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence Editorial Project Records document the research, planning, editing, publishing, and marketing of W. S. Lewis's scholarly edition of the correspondence of Horace Walpole (1717-1797), issued in forty-eight volumes between 1937 and 1983 by Yale University Press.
Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979
Kilby, Clyde S., 1902-1986
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (Yale 1918), 1979.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Administrative Records, 1936-1983. II. Editorial Documents, 1900-1982. III. The Horace Walpole Diurnal, undated. IV. Clyde S. Kilby Notes on Walpole as a Literary Critic, circa 1945.
Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (1895-1979)
Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis was born in Alameda, California, on November 14, 1895, the son of Miranda Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis and Azro Nathaniel Lewis. He attended the Thacher School in Ojai, California, and Yale University (Class of 1918). He met Annie Burr Auchincloss (1902-1959) in Farmington, Connecticut, in 1923, and the couple were married in 1928. Together they spent three decades building a collection of books, prints, paintings, manuscripts, and decorative arts related to Horace Walpole, his circle, and his time, and formed a research library at their home in Farmington. Wilmarth Lewis died in Hartford on October 7, 1979; he left his home and collections to Yale University by bequest.
The Yale Edition Editorial Staff
Wilmarth Lewis served as editor for forty-two of the forty-eight volumes of the Yale Edition, but most of the work was accomplished by the editorial staff in "The Walpole Factory" at Sterling Memorial Library on the campus of Yale University in New Haven.
The volumes, Walpole correspondents, editorial staff, and publication dates were: Volumes 1–2: William Cole (A. Dayle Wallace, 1937); Volumes 3–8: Madame du Deffand (Warren Hunting Smith, 1939); Volumes 9–10: George Montagu (Ralph S. Brown Jr., 1941); Volumes 11–12: Mary and Agnes Berry and Barbara Cecilia Seton (A. Dayle Wallace, 1944); Volumes 13–14: Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton (George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948); Volume 15: David Dalrymple and others (Charles H. Bennett and Andrew G. Hoover, 1951); Volume 16: Thomas Chatterton and others (A. Dayle Wallace, 1951); Volumes 17–27: Sir Horace Mann (Warren Hunting Smith and George L. Lam, 1954–1971); Volumes 28–29: William Mason (Grover Cronin Jr. and Charles H. Bennett, 1955); Volume 30: George Selwyn and others (Robert A. Smith, 1961); Volume 31: Hannah More and others (Robert A. Smith and Charles H. Bennett, 1961); Volumes 32–34: Countess of Upper Ossory (A. Dayle Wallace, 1965); Volume 35: John Chute and others (A. Dayle Wallace and Robert A. Smith, 1973); Volume 36: the Walpole family (Joseph W. Reed Jr., 1973); Volumes 37–39: Henry Seymour Conway and others (Lars E. Troide, Edwine M. Martz, and Robert A. Smith, 1974); Volumes 40–42: miscellaneous correspondence (John C. Riely, 1980); Volume 43: additions and corrections, subject index to illustrations, index of Horace Walpole's correspondents, chronological list of letters (compilied by Edwine M. Martz, 1983); and Volumes 44–48: complete index (compiled by Warren Hunting Smith, 1983). Assistant editors during the project were Edwine Martz, Ruth K. McClure, and William T. LaMoy.
Related Materials
Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20). The Lewis Walpole Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence Editorial Project Records document the full scope of the publication effort over its nearly fifty-year span. Series I, Administrative Records ranges from agreements with Yale University Press, style guides, and editorial exemplars, to the office door sign that hung in the hallway in Yale University Library. Also present are the records of the two Yale Edition celebrations, one held in 1973 for the project's fortieth anniversary, and one in 1983 for the project's completion. Series II, Editorial Documents, contains material in a variety of formats to show the methods employed during the project: autograph manuscript and typescript texts, printed galleys, and page proofs for both the letters and the volume indexes. Also here are a few letters between Wilmarth Lewis and the project's dozen other editors, as well as correspondence with foreign research associates, particularly those in Italy who assisted with the Horace Mann letters. The bulk of the series concerns the Mann-Walpole correspondence, which was edited primarily by George L. Lam and Warren Hunting Smith and published in eleven volumes between 1954 and 1971; their transcriptions and notes were specifically marked for retention because some of their research had not been incorporated into their published work.
Twelve binders with chronological notes on Walpole's daily activities and correspondents comprise Series III, The Horace Walpole Diurnal. Series IV holds a box of material sampled from Clyde S. Kilby's unfinished research on Horace Walpole's efforts in literary criticism. Kilby's work had already been superseded by the Yale Edition's extensive annotations and indexes when he donated his files to Lewis in 1949.
Separated Materials
Printed material found within the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Editors -- United States; Galley proofs; Page proofs; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; Bagnani, Gilbert, 1900-1985; Bennett, Charles H. (Charles Hodges), 1906-; Chapman, R. W. (Robert William), 1881-1960; Erskine, David; Hazen, Allen T. (Allen Tracy), 1904-1977; Ketton-Cremer, R. W. (Robert Wyndham), 1906-1969; Kilby, Clyde S., 1902-1986; Lam, George L. (George Lorant), 1909-1970; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; Mann, Horace, Sir, 1701-1786; Morshead, O. F., Sir (Owen Frederick), 1893-; Namier, L. B. (Lewis Bernstein), 1888-1960; Sartini, Ferdinando, 1878-1955; Smith, Robert A. (Robert Arthur), 1926-; Smith, Warren Hunting, 1905-1998; Troide, Lars E., 1942-; Wallace, A. Dayle (Alva Dayle), 1908-1973; Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797
- Administrative Records, 1936–1983; Series I; 4.6; 9 boxes + 2 broadsides + 1 roll
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Editorial Office Files and Event Records.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains the extant administrative records of the edition retained after Wilmarth Lewis's death. The first subseries, Editorial Office Files, is comprised of a variety of documents ranging from the memoranda of agreement for the publication of the series and style sheets prepared for use of the editors, to working surveys of Walpole's correspondence and bibliographic notes by the New Haven editorial staff, and samples of edits made by members of the project's editorial board. Also here are printed circulars, prospectuses, announcements, and Yale University Press catalogues showing how the edition was marketed and publicized over the decades. The second subseries, Event Records, holds administrative records of the celebrations organized in 1973 to mark the edition's fortieth anniversary, and in 1983 to mark the completion of the project.
  The records in the series are a miscellaneous collection of papers which span the length of the project in time, but most certainly do not encompass the variety of records that were kept by the administrative or editorial staff. They are not complete or extensive, and appear to have been selected primarily to document decisions made in respect to editorial practice. Most noticeably absent is any substantial correspondence between Wilmarth Lewis in Farmington and the two dozen members of the editorial staff in New Haven over the project's five decades: Charles H. Bennett, Ralph S. Brown Jr., Grover Cronin, Andrew G. Hoover, George L. Lam, Edwine M. Martz, Ruth K. McClure, Joseph W. Reed, Robert A. Smith, Warren Hunting Smith, Lars E. Troide, and A. Dayle Wallace. Letters between Lewis and his colleagues, extensive correspondence with George Lam and Warren Smith in particular, remains as Lewis had filed it in Series I of the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20).
  Also absent here are letters between Lewis, the staff, and the members of the project's valuable advisory committee, most of whom lived in England. Readers should look in Series I of Lewis's papers for correspondence with R. W. Chapman, R. W. Ketton-Cremer, O. F. Morshead, L. B. Namier, and Leonard Whibley, and others.
  - Editorial Office Files
    - Acknowledgements lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Photocopies of lists appearing at the front of the volumes.
    - Census of Walpole letters, 1950–1951 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      Two three-ring binders holding records created by the correspondence project staff that enumerate letters to and from Walpole that had been published in earlier correspondence editions (Berry, Wright, Cunningham, and Toynbee), letters owned by Lewis and other owners, and letters missing; the lists are alphabetical by correspondent.
      The first binder also holds a "List of present and former owners of HW MSS" dated April 1950. The second volume was kept by George Lam.
      It is possible that the correspondent data in these records was used to create the "Index of Horace Walpole's Correspondents" found on pages 427-442 of Volume 43; the published list does not enumerate missing letters (accounted for in the binders).
    - Dinner invitation and table chart, 1961 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      Letter from George Lam to W. S. Lewis, inviting him to a "buffet supper of eighteenth century dishes for the Walpole Factory" at his home. It is accompanied by five photocopies of the table layout, each with a different hand-colored design featuring caricatures of Lewis, Walpole, and others.
    - Door sign from Sterling Memorial Library, circa 1940 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 2)
      Hallway identification sign for the editorial project's offices.
    - Editorial exemplars
      This selection of corrected galleys and editorial notes was likely made by Yale University Library staff after Wilmarth Lewis's death. Most of the galleys appear to be related to the Walpole-Mann correspondence volumes, but were meant to represent the quality of work undertaken across the span of the project. Other editorial corrections made directly on full-sheet galleys can be found in Series II, in particular the galleys for volumes 1 and 2.
      - R. W. Chapman corrections, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - David Erskine corrections, 1958–1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - R. W. Ketton-Cremer corrections, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - W. S. Lewis corrections, 1949–1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Owen Morshead corrections, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Lewis Namier corrections, 1952–1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Robert A. Smith corrections, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Staff corrections, 1947–1955 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Geographic index to correspondents, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Horace Walpole's Set of Detached Pieces Printed at Strawberry-Hill", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Typescript carbon of a transcription from microfilm.
    - Map of subscribers, 1965 January 14 (Box 81 (Broadside))
      Two copies of a Cleartype map of the United States with state outlines, one copy annotated with the numbers of Yale edition subscribers in each state, with foreign countries enumerated in the lower margin.
    - Memoranda of agreement, 1937–1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Legal agreements signed by Yale University, Yale University Press, and Wilmarth and Annie Lewis, covering the publication of series. Also present is the first invoice for the production of Volumes 1 and 2, Rev. William Cole correspondence.
    - Poem by R. W. Ketton-Cremer, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Typescript, with copies, of "Lines to Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis, to welcome the appearance of the first volumes of his edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence, October 5, 1937."
    - Portrait of George L. Lam, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Snapshot photograph taken in Yale Library courtyard by Bob Warnock, October 1958
    - Project publicity
      - Circular letters, 1936–1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        Letters sent to librarians and educators announcing the editorial project and the publication of the different volumes.
      - Yale Library Associates announcement, 1937 September (Box 3, Folder 15)
        Postcard announcing publication celebration including a lecture by W. S. Lewis and an exhibition of Walpoliana from his collection.
      - Newspaper advertisements, 1948; 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Advertisements torn from the Times, stating that Wilmarth Lewis seeks Walpole correspondence for the Yale Edition. Two other ads, dated 1935 and 1953, are pasted inside the front cover of Lewis's personal scrapbook (LWL MSS 20).
      - Prospectus, circa 1936 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        Prospectus for the edition.
      - Prospectuses and announcements, 1936–1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
        Advertising for various volumes.
      - Oxford University Press order form, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Reviews (extracts, compiled), 1938–1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        Likely compiled for use in publicity efforts. Many other clipped reviews can be found in scrapbooks held in LWL MSS 20, Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers.
      - Yale University Press
        - Catalogue, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        - Catalogues and ephemera, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 22)
        - Catalogues and ephemera, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 23)
          Includes a brochure in Japanese.
        - Catalogues and ephemera, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Robert A. Smith's notebooks, 1949–1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Inscribed by George Lam: "Robert A. Smith Notebooks on readings in sale catalogues at BM 1949-1950."
    - Stationery and forms, 1938–1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Includes variant letterheads and examples of cards created for recording Walpole correspondence and ephemera.
    - Style decision documents
      The material in this section was grouped together in a file drawer with the accompanying note in an unknown hand: "The material in this drawer, like the Cole proofs and manuscript, is being kept because it concerns the styling of the edition. Once a policy of style was arrived at, consistency was striven for."
      - Card index, undated (Box 5)
        Wooden box of cards and slips with accompanying paper slip: "Index showing our usage for capitals, italics, etc. in the Yale Walpole." The label was further annotated by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "No need to keep indefinitely. Use of this is over." At the end of the file are bibliographic cards and library call slips, likely for books used by editors.
      - Cue titles and abbreviations, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Footnote indexing, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Mann indexing, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Style sheets and notes, 1936–1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Booklets assembled for the use of the editorial staff.
      - Style sheets from other editorial projects, 1956–1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        Guides from the Johnson and Boswell editorial projects.
      - Text normalization, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Titles and courtesy titles, 1948–1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Variant spellings in Gray, Mann, and Walpole letters, undated (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
        Notes and paper slips recording some of the variant spellings found during the project
    - Subscribers and complimentary lists, 1954–1983 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Lists of subscribers to the volumes, and of those otherwise receiving complimentary copies.
    - Survey of State Papers, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Typescript of "Survey of State Papers Foreign and Domestic, Foreign Office and Home Office Records, 1 Hen. VIII (1509) to 40 Geo. III (1799) in the Public Record Office and the Newcastle Papers and Hardwicke Papers in the British Museum," compiled by George L. Lam and John R. Forrest, with an introduction by Lam. Accompanied by own Lam's annotated typescript carbon bearing a note on John Forrest's death on October 25, 1952.
    - "Tools" (Box 80, Folder 1)
      Folder of miscellaneous lists, inventories, notes, and correspondence found in Wilmarth Lewis's general correspondence (LWL MSS 20); it was moved to the edition records in July 2018.
    - "Walpole and Newcastle" by George L. Lam, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, of an essay.
    - Walpole and Newcastle notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Walpole bibliography, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Pages removed from Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature, and given to George Lam by Wilmarth Lewis on April 4, 1941.
    - Walpole family genealogical chart, undated (Box 82 (Broadside))
      A chart of descent from King Henry III through two generations of Horace Walpole's nephews and nieces; mounted on pulpboard measuring 30 by 40 inches.
    - Walpole genealogical table, undated (Box 83 (Roll))
      Twentieth-century copy of "A genealogical table of all the kings and princes of Wales from Cadwalader last King of Britain to Lhewelyn last Prince of Wales of the British blood: with the descent of his present Majesty King George, as also of the Right Honourable Robert Lord Walpole, from Cadwalader" (LWL 49 2624); measures 59.5 by 24 inches when unrolled.
    - Walpole's finances, circa 1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Photocopy of research notes and correspondence by George Lam
    - Other notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Event Records
    - Mann correspondence dinner, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Lewis often held celebratory dinners at the conclusion of volumes. In October 1971 he hosted a group of colleagues at the Lawn Club in New Haven to celebrate the publication of the Horace Mann letters.
    - "Jubilee"
      Filed here are records of the "Jubilee," a celebration held in October 1973 to mark the fortieth anniversary of the editorial project and the publication of Volumes 35 and 36. Events included three Walpole-related exhibitions (one each at Yale's Beinecke and Sterling Memorial libraries, and at the Watkinson Library, Trinity College), a concert sponsored by the Yale University Library Associates, and two dinners in New Haven (for the advisory committee on October 18 and for invited guests of the university president on October 19), both of which featured speakers. In addition, Wilmarth Lewis was interviewed and videotaped for the "Yale '73" television series on October 16th, and delivered the University Lecture at the Yale Law School on October 19th.
      Two publications resulted from the jubilee: the Beinecke's exhibition catalogue A Guide to the Life of Horace Walpole (New Haven: Yale University Press for the Yale University Library, 1973), and an issue of the Yale University Library Gazette (volume 48, number 2, October 1973) which presented Wilmarth Lewis's speech, "The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence, 1933-1973," the program of the concert, and the catalogue of the Sterling Memorial Library's exhibition, "The Age of Horace Walpole in Caricature: An Exhibition of Satirical Prints and Drawings from the Collection of W. S. Lewis."
      - Associates concert, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Dinner: Advisory Committee, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Dinner: President Kingman Brewster, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Exhibitions
        - Beinecke Library, Yale, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
        - Sterling Memorial Library, Yale, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Watkinson Library, Trinity College, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Jubilee brochure, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Mailing lists, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Planning notes, 1972–1973 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Publicity, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
      - Speeches, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - [On the Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence], 1973 (Box 7, Folder 14)
        Copy of a corrected galley for an essay in the Yale Alumni Magazine (November 1973), based on his October speech.
      - "Yale '73" Television Series interview, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Celebration
      A second celebration was held on September 14, 1983, to mark the completion of the editorial project. The events included a lecture by Warren H. Smith, associate editor of the correspondence and compiler of the final index; a reception and exhibition viewing at Beinecke Library; and a dinner for eighty held in the President's Room at Woolsey Hall.
      - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Event notes, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Exhibition pieces, 1983 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 3)
        Materials kept from the exhibition at Beinecke Library include the exhibition signs, a chart of Yale University Libraries, and lists of the Advisory Committee members and editors involved throughout the project.
      - Expenses, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Invitations and response cards, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Mailing lists, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Publicity, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Warren H. Smith speech, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Warren H. Smith speech offprints, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Editorial Documents, 1934–1982; Series II; 28.6; 70 boxes + 1 broadside
  Series II is organized into ten subseries and arranged by volume number.
  The series contains material in a variety of formats to show the methods employed during the project: autograph manuscript and typescript texts, printed galleys, and page proofs for both the letters and the volume indexes. Also found here is some correspondence between Wilmarth Lewis and the project's dozen other editors, though most of their correspondence is filed in Series I of the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20).
  The bulk of the series concerns the Mann-Walpole correspondence, which was edited primarily by George L. Lam and Warren Hunting Smith and published in eleven volumes between 1954 and 1971; their transcriptions and notes were specifically marked for retention because some of their research had not been incorporated into their published work.
  The earliest material in the series are annotated pages removed from Mrs. Paget Toynbee's 1912 book of letters between Walpole and Madame du Deffand.
  - Volumes 1-2: The Reverend William Cole
    This material was retained by library staff with a note in an unidentified hand: "The Cole proofs and manuscript are to be kept because they illustrate some of the evolutionary process that occurred at the outset of the edition. Questions of style and format, for example, had to be settled."
    - Preface, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Typescript, corrected
    - Manuscript, pages 2-1063, circa 1936 (Box 9, Folder 2-5)
    - Manuscript, pages 1064-2252, circa 1937 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Galley, front matter, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Galleys, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
      Some with corrections by R. W. Chapman and "Bill."
    - Revised galley, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Second revised galleys, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Page proof galleys, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Revised page proof galleys, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Index galley, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Volume 1 page proofs, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Volume 2 page proofs, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Volumes 3-8: Madame du Deffand
    The papers here were kept with a note by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "One box - Warren H. Smith's papers on Du Deffand material. There may be information here that was not published in the Du Deffand volumes of HW's Corr. Keep."